Guide to the Theodore Francis Jones Papers MC.28
New York University Archives
Theodore Francis Jones Papers
1913-1955
New York University Archives
Jones, Theodore Francis, 1885-1968
MC.28
2 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes
Theodore Francis Jones was born in Dover, Massachusetts on December 5, 1885. He joined the Department of History at New York University as an instructor in 1910 and was assistant professor, 1920-1924, and professor, 1924-1951. He also served as Director of Gould Memorial Library on the University Heights campus from 1925 to 1948. His book, New York University, 1832-1932, was published in 1933 as part of the university's centennial celebration. Upon his retirement in 1951, Jones was awarded an honorary degree by NYU. He died on November 18, 1968. The collection contains research notes, official and military correspondence, reports, and the manuscript of New York University, 1832-1932.
Provenance
The papers were transferred to the University Archives from the University Heights Campus when the campus closed in 1973. They were presumably part of the New York University Historical Collection of the Gould Memorial Library.
Separated Material
The World War II Heights Memorial Collection of photographs (2 linear feet, .5 boxes), which is pertinent to Series II of the papers has been removed to the University Archives Photograph Collection.
Arrangement Note
The collection is arranged into three series.
Missing Title
Series I: Subject File, 1924-1955
Series II: World War II Record, 1943-1955
Series III: Manuscripts and Publications, 1913-1945
Historical/Biographical Note
Theodore Francis Jones was born in Dover, Massachusetts on December 5, 1885. After graduation from the Boston Latin School, he proceeded to Harvard, where he received his A.B. in 1906. During the next year, he studied at the École Libre des Sciences Politiques in Paris. From 1908-1910, he was an assistant in History at Harvard and received his Ph.D. from that institution in 1910. He joined the Department of History at New York University as an instructor in 1910 and was assistant professor, 1912-1920, associate professor, 1920-1924, and professor, 1924-1951. In addition, he served as Director of the University Heights Library from 1925-1948. From 1917-1921, Professor Jones was a lieutenant in the Naval Reserves and in 1918 he served as Assistant Naval Attaché in Madrid.
Jones' most important publication was New York University, 1832-1932, published in 1933 as part of NYU's Centennial Celebration. He was also the author of Land Ownership in Brookline, Mass. (1923), and co-author (with Professor Richard Davis Mallory) of a centennial memoir entitled The Presidents of the Beta of N.Y. Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa, published in 1958. Although he never chose to publish his findings, Jones was recognized by many scholars as one of the leading experts on Venetian trade with England in the later Middle Ages.
Upon his retirement in 1951, Jones was awarded an honorary degree by New York University. He died on November 18, 1968.
Conditions Governing Access
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains notes and background materials pertaining to Jones' research on land ownership, New York University history, and World War II. It also contains official and military correspondence, reports, and the manuscript of New York University, 1832-1932.
World War, 1939-1945 -- History.; Land settlement -- History; Edmondson, Thomas William, 1869-1938; Irwin, John V.; Stokes, I. N. Phelps (Isaac Newton Phelps), 1867-1944; Botta, Anne C. Lynch (Anne Charlotte Lynch), 1815-1891; Bouton, Archibald Lewis, 1872-1941; Butler, Charles, 1802-1897; New York University -- Alumni; New England Historic Genealogical Society; New York University. Faculty of Arts and Science; New York University. Libraries; New York University -- History
- Series I: Subject Files, 1924-1955
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I: Subject File, 1924-1955, is arranged alphabetically by content and contains research notes to various books, articles, and lectures given by Jones, as well as official correspondence and reports Jones wrote in his capacity as Library Director. Included is correspondence for 1931-1946 and research notes on Bronx land ownership [Box 1, folders 5-7], which indicates that Jones was considering a companion piece to his 1923 book Land Ownership in Brookline, Mass. In addition, there are undated research notes of colonial land ownership in White Plains, New York [Box 2, folder 12]. Also of interest is Jones' correspondence with John V. Irwin, NYU class of 1894, who offered a series of comments and corrections to New York University, 1832-1932.
  - Archer, Donald: Archer Genealogy, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Botta, Anna Lynch: References to, 1924-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bouton, Archibald Lewis: Corresondence - RESTRICTED, 1927-1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Conditions Governing Access
    RESTRICTED
  - Bouton, Archibald Lewis: Library, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bronx, Land Ownership: Corresondence, 1931-1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bronx, Land Ownership: Research Index Cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bronx, Land Ownership: Research Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Butler, Charles: References to, 1933-1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Edmondson, Thomas William: Correspondence, 1934-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gibbon, Edward: References to, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Italian Books: Correspondence Concerning, 1934-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Library, Office of the Director: Annual Report, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Library, Office of the Director: Correspondence, circa 1933-1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Muller, Louis Anathe: References to, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - New England Historic Genealogical Society, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - New York University Collection, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - NYKL, A. R.: KRS The Death of a Myth (pamphlet), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Osborn, George W.: Collection of Books, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photostat Copies of Colonial Documents, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Recordings, Faculty: Correspondence Concerning, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Richards, John: Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Stokes Foundation Lectures, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Stokes, I.N. Phelps: Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Subscription Book No. 10: Typescript Copy, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Tompkins, Leslie J.: Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Turkish Collection: Correspondence Concerning, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - University Forum, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - University Seal (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - White Plains, Land Ownership: Research Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Works Progress Administration (WPA), undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series II: World War II Records, 1943-1955
  Series II: World War II Record, 1943-1955, is arranged alphabetically by content and is concerned with alumni and former employees who served in the armed services during World War II. It contains military correspondence between Jones and former employees and students in the service during World War II showing Dr. Jones' concern with creating a scrapbook detailing the activities of university servicemen during the war. This concern evolved into the creation of a photographic war memorial to alumni who were war-related casualties. His correspondence with university officials seeking funding and appropriate space for the memorial and correspondence with the friends and relatives of the deceased demonstrate his efforts in creating this memorial. The folders also include photographs of the servicemen and letters from families expressing their appreciation.
  - Bulletin of NYU Glee Club ("Lest We Forget"), undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Adair, James C. to Aron, Jerome, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Bartolone, Anthony to Butler, Manfred, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Cantor, Jerome C. to Clark, Bradley B., undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Clark, Warren J. to Cummings, Edward, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Dearborn, Gayle to Friedman, Leonard, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Garland, John J. to Greenberg, Irving, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Halpern, Leonard to Johnson, George, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: Kallek, Nathan R. to Krusi, John B., undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: Laufer, Lester to Luter, Roland, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Macord, Ralph H. to Mosner, Solomon D., undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Neuweiler, Arthur to Ogur, Warren, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Pager, Harold K. to Prossen, Peter J., undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Raskin, Marvin J. to Rubin, Stanley, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Salus, Joseph to Sydlowski, Stanley, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Turner, Jarry J. to Vincent, Nicholas, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Waldraer, James A. to Zilver, Herbert V., undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Lists: Former Employees in the Armed Services, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lists: War-Related Casualties, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Services Record of Former Employees: Alderman, Harry to Volin, Maurice F., undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - University Service in World War II, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - War Memorial Correspondence: Bialick, Irving to Ross, Benjamin, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Glass plate negatives, undated (Box Shared University Archives 019)
- Series III: Manuscripts and Publications, 1913-1945
  Series III: Manuscripts and Publications, 1913-1945, is arranged alphabetically by title, and includes published books and articles, as well as the typed manuscript of the university history, New York University, 1832-1932, including some research notes and information [Box 4, folders 6-10].
  - The Archives of the Venetian Republic, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Land Ownership in Brookline, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - New York University, 1832-1932 Manuscript: Chapters I-V, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - New York University, 1832-1932 Manuscript: Chapters VI-X, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - New York University, 1832-1932 Manuscript: Chapters XI-XVI, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - New York University, 1832-1932 Manuscript: Appendix A-G, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - New York University, 1832-1932 Manuscript: Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Roster of the Expedition of 1690 to Canada, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)